<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- This is an automatically generated file. -->
<Chapter Label="Chapter_Using_general_tools_HTML_canvas_D3">
<Heading>Using general tools (HTML, canvas, D3)</Heading>

<P/>
<Section Label="Chapter_Using_general_tools_HTML_canvas_D3_Section_Why_these_tools_are_present">
<Heading>Why these tools are present</Heading>

<P/>
These general tools can be used as building blocks to create other
custom visualization tools. As a first example, the canvas tool
installs an HTML canvas element and then lets you draw arbitrary shapes
on it with JavaScript code. As a second example, some of the high-level
tools this package imports were built on top of D3, a foundational
visualization toolkit, which you can access directly.
<P/>
First, we cover an as-yet-unmentioned feature of
<Ref Func="CreateVisualization"/> that lets us make use of such general
tools.
<P/>
</Section>


<Section Label="Chapter_Using_general_tools_HTML_canvas_D3_Section_Post-processing_visualizations">
<Heading>Post-processing visualizations</Heading>

<P/>
The <Ref Func="CreateVisualization"/> function
takes an optional second parameter, a string of JavaScript code to be
run once the visualization has been rendered. For example, if the
visualization library you were using did not support adding borders
around a visualization, but you wanted to add one, you could add it by
writing one line of JavaScript code to run after the visualization was
rendered.
<P/>
<Log><![CDATA[
CreateVisualization(
    rec(
        # put your data here, as in previous sections
    ),
    "visualization.style.border = '5px solid black'"
)
]]></Log>


<P/>
This holds for any visualization tool, not just AnyChart. In the code
given in the second parameter, two variables will be defined for your
use: <Code>element</Code> refers to the output cell element in the
notebook and <Code>visualization</Code> refers to the visualization that
the toolkit you chose created within that output cell (also an HTML
element).
<P/>
Now that we know that we can run arbitrary JavaScript code on a
visualization once it's been produced, we can call
<Ref Func="CreateVisualization"/> to produce rather empty results, then
fill them using our own JavaScript code. The next section explains
how this could be done to create custom visualizations.
<P/>
</Section>


<Section Label="Section_plainhtml">
<Heading>Injecting JavaScript into general tools</Heading>

<P/>
<Subsection Label="Chapter_Using_general_tools_HTML_canvas_D3_Section_Injecting_JavaScript_into_general_tools_Subsection_Example_Native_HTML_Canvas">
<Heading>Example: Native HTML Canvas</Heading>

<P/>
You can create a blank canvas, then use the existing JavaScript canvas
API to draw on it. This example is trivial, but more complex examples
are possible.
<P/>
<Log><![CDATA[
CreateVisualization(
    rec( tool := "canvas", height := 300 ),
    """
    // visualization is the canvas element
    var context = visualization.getContext( '2d' );
    // draw an X
    context.moveTo( 0, 0 );
    context.lineTo( 100, 100 );
    context.moveTo( 100, 0 );
    context.lineTo( 0, 100 );
    context.stroke();
    """
);
]]></Log>


<P/>
<Alt Only="LaTeX">
\begin{center}
\includegraphics{canvas-example.png}
\end{center}
</Alt>
<Alt Only="HTML"><![CDATA[<img width="200" src="canvas-example.png"/>]]></Alt>
<Alt Not="LaTeX HTML">Resulting image not shown here.</Alt>
<P/>
</Subsection>


<Subsection Label="Chapter_Using_general_tools_HTML_canvas_D3_Section_Injecting_JavaScript_into_general_tools_Subsection_Example_Plain_HTML">
<Heading>Example: Plain HTML</Heading>

<P/>
This is the degenerate example of a visualization. It does not create
any visualization, but lets you specify arbitrary HTML content instead.
It is provided here merely as a convenient way to insert HTML into the
notebook.
<P/>
<Log><![CDATA[
CreateVisualiation(
    rec(
        tool := "html",
        data := rec(
            html := "<i>Any</i> HTML can go here.  Tables, buttons, whatever."
        )
    ),
    """
    // Here you could install event handlers on tools created above.
    // For example, if you had created a button with id="myButton":
    var button = document.getElementById( "myButton" );
    button.addEventListener( "click", function () {
        alert( "My button was clicked." );
    } );
    """
);
]]></Log>


<P/>
When writing such JavaScript code, note that you have access to a useful
function that this package has installed, <Code>runGAP</Code>. Its
signature is <Code>runGAP(stringToEvaluate,callback)</Code> and the
following code shows an example of how you could call it from JavaScript
in the notebook.
<P/>
<Log><![CDATA[
runGAP( "2^100;", function ( result, error ) {
    if ( result )
        alert( "2^100 = " + result );
    else
        alert( "GAP gave this error: " + error );
} );
]]></Log>


<P/>
</Subsection>


<Subsection Label="Chapter_Using_general_tools_HTML_canvas_D3_Section_Injecting_JavaScript_into_general_tools_Subsection_Example_D3">
<Heading>Example: D3</Heading>

<P/>
While D3 is one of the most famous and powerful JavaScript visualization
libraries, it does not have a JSON interface. Consequently, we can
interact with D3 only through the JavaScript code passed in the second
parameter to <Ref Func="CreateVisualization"/>. This makes it much less
convenient, but we include it in this package for those who need it.
<P/>
<Log><![CDATA[
CreateVisualization(
    rec( tool := "d3" ),
    """
    // arbitrary JavaScript code can go here to interact with D3, like so:
    d3.select( visualization ).append( "circle" )
        .attr( "r", 50 ).attr( "cx", 55 ).attr( "cy", 55 )
        .style( "stroke", "red" ).style( "fill", "pink" );
    """
);
]]></Log>


<P/>
<Alt Only="LaTeX">
\begin{center}
\includegraphics{d3-example.png}
\end{center}
</Alt>
<Alt Only="HTML"><![CDATA[<img width="200" src="d3-example.png"/>]]></Alt>
<Alt Not="LaTeX HTML">Resulting image not shown here.</Alt>
</Subsection>


</Section>


</Chapter>

